<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<article xmlns="http://www.newinchess.com/standards" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
    forSection="cafe" year="2013" issue="2" id="NIC_2013_02_006_cafe_4">
    <info>
        <title>Sweet dreams</title>
        <author>
            <firstname>Dirk Jan</firstname>
            <surname>ten Geuzendam</surname>
            <affiliation>Editorial Board</affiliation>
        </author>
        <abstract>
            <para>The Alekhine Memorial: Andrei Filatov brings art and chess together</para>
        </abstract>
        <teaser priority="00">Andrei Filatov brings together art and chess</teaser>
    </info>
    <para>Andrei Filatov is a man with many dreams. When he staged the World Championship match in
        the Moscow Tretyakov Gallery he fulfilled one of them, but the Russian businessman
        immediately made it clear that he had further visions of bringing chess and art together.
        One of them was an Alekhine Memorial in the Louvre in Paris. Many months of complicated
        negotiations followed, but finally Filatov could announce another unique double success. To
        begin with he and his business partner Gennady Timchenko signed an agreement with Henri
        Loyrette, the Director of the Louvre Museum, ‘to support the expansion of the Louvre’s
        collection in the area of Russian art’. Currently, the collection of the Louvre only
        includes ancient Russian icons. As part of the agreement, they will expand its collection by
        adding Russian paintings. And indeed the Louvre will open its doors for chess as well. On
        April 21 the first round of the Alekhine Memorial will be played in the museum complex.
        After five rounds the tournament will move to the Mikhailovsky Palace of the State Russian
        Museum in St. Petersburg for the final four rounds. The names of the players? Vishy Anand,
        Levon Aronian, Vladimir Kramnik, Peter Svidler, Boris Gelfand, Nikita Vitiugov, Mickey
        Adams, Maxime Vachier-Lagrave, Laurent Fressinet and Ding Liren. <inlinemediaobject>
            <imageobject>
                <imagedata align="left" depth="4256" width="2832"
                    fileref="../images/cafe/filatov%20ClosingMoscow%20029.JPG"/>
            </imageobject>
            <caption>Andrei Filatov: Tretyakov Gallery, the Louvre, what’s next?</caption>
            <photographer>
                <firstname/>
                <surname>New In Chess</surname>
            </photographer>
        </inlinemediaobject></para>
</article>
