<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<article xmlns="http://www.newinchess.com/standards" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
    forSection="cafe" year="2013" issue="2" id="NIC_2013_02_006_cafe_3">
    <info>
        <title>Watching with the stars</title>
        <author>
            <firstname>Dirk Jan</firstname>
            <surname>ten Geuzendam</surname>
            <affiliation>Editorial Board</affiliation>
        </author>
        <abstract>
            <para>After his sweeping victory in Wijk aan Zee, Magnus Carlsen felt he had deserved a
                break</para>
        </abstract>
        <teaser priority="00">Magnus Carlsen: Watching with the stars </teaser>
    </info>
    <para>After his sweeping victory in Wijk aan Zee, Magnus Carlsen felt he had deserved a break
        and of course no one was going to argue with that. Eager to divert his mind, he travelled to
        the United States. The first days were still filled with business, including an event in Las
        Vegas with his new American sponsor Parallels (‘a worldwide leader in hosting and cloud
        service enablement and desktop virtualization’) but then it was time for some fun. Together
        with a friend he went to see a number of basketball matches in Boston, Philadelphia and New
        York. In Madison Square Garden he saw the New York Knicks take on the LA Clippers. It’s not
        easy to get good tickets for such matches, but if you’re well connected you may even get
        ringside tickets! And there he was, in second row, seated behind Hollywood celebrities Tom
        Hanks, Christopher McDonald, Olivia Wilde, Jason Sudeikis, Ben Stiller and Christine Taylor.
        While they seem to feel comfortable with the attention of the photographers, the Norwegian
        looks less thrilled by the attention of the paparazzi. <inlinemediaobject>
            <imageobject>
                <imagedata align="left" depth="681" width="834"
                    fileref="../images/cafe/carlsen%201360653775684_701.jpg"/>
            </imageobject>
            <caption>Seated behind Tom Hanks and his buddies, Magnus Carlsen watches the New York
                Knicks vs. the LA Clippers in Madison Square Garden.</caption>
            <photographer>
                <firstname/>
                <surname/>
            </photographer>
        </inlinemediaobject></para>
</article>
