<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<article xmlns="http://www.newinchess.com/standards" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
    forSection="cafe" year="2013" issue="2" id="NIC_2013_02_006_cafe_2">
    <info>
        <title> What is a rule?</title>
        <author>
            <firstname>Dirk</firstname>
            <surname>Ten Geuzedam</surname>
            <affiliation>Editorial Board</affiliation>
        </author>
        <abstract>
            <para>Among the most common measures these days to keep players from making short draws
                are the anti-drawing rules that forbid them to end a game peacefully before a
                certain number of moves have been made.</para>
        </abstract>
        <teaser priority="00">Nikita Vitiugov: ‘It isn’t a rule when somebody can break
            it.’</teaser>
    </info>
    <para>Among the most common measures these days to keep players from making short draws are the
        anti-drawing rules that forbid them to end a game peacefully before a certain number of
        moves have been made. Despite repeated criticism, these rules have been remarkably
        successful, which in itself says a lot about the ambitions of many chess players when they
        are not forced to play. Still, these anti-drawing rules are not always effective, as witness
        this year’s Gibraltar Chess Congress. One of the highlights were the varied and popular
        ‘Master Classes’, and the most popular of the five presented this year was by Vassily
        Ivanchuk, who was highly animated as he took questions from the audience and host Stuart
        Conquest for nearly half an hour. The Master Class was ostensibly a form of penance, for a
        minor infraction of the tournament rule. Earlier in the day, Ivanchuk’s seventh round
        pairing with Le Quang Liem ended after just fourteen moves in an equal and symmetrical
        position, while the tournament regulations mandated that games be played out to at least
        move 30. The players had left the playing hall before the anomaly was noticed by the
        arbiters and the organizers, who initially considered requiring the game to be replayed. Le
        actually remained near the hall for quite some time awaiting a decision from his opponent,
        who was reluctant to return. Ivanchuk, evidently, was in no mood to replay the game.
        Ironically, a similarly quick draw occurred between two amateur players during the same
        round, and they were in fact asked to replay their game. Ultimately the matter was simply
        dropped. The comment of later winner Nikita Vitiugov was nicely succinct: ‘It isn’t a rule
        when somebody can break it.’
        <inlinemediaobject>
            <imageobject>
                <imagedata align="left" depth="1040" width="1600"
                    fileref="../images/cafe/conquest%20and%20ivanchuk%20Img_8182.jpg"/>
            </imageobject>
            <caption>Having saved energy earlier in the day, Vassily Ivanchuk was ready to answer
                any question Stuart Conquest could think of.</caption>
            <photographer>
                <firstname>Macauley</firstname>
                <surname>Peterson</surname>
            </photographer>
        </inlinemediaobject></para>
</article>
